Tired of searching for subtitles?
Ray generates them instantly: getray.app
Michael:
I was in my office at work
and I got a call
from an international number.
Through the last
three years.
when it was
an international call.
I'd answer it.
It was a reporter in Dublin
who wanted a reaction
to the story.
I said.
"Reaction for what?"
They were really caught back
by that question. obviously.
And they said.
"I'll call you back
in five minutes."
And so then I went online
and saw the picture.
It's not the way
you want to find out.
I never. ever imagined
that it would end
in that fashion. right?
For days that first week.
I just would constantly
see that image and...
It's been tough.
You go through
those emotional swings.
"Why the hell
did you go back
that second time?"
But I keep coming back
to the same answer.
Host:
Name the sports newspaper
that hit US newsstands
in 1990.
- ( buzzer sounds )
- James?
- "The National."
- It was.
Man:
Ladies and gentlemen.
please help me welcome
Mr. James Foley.
( applause )
Thanks for that generous--
- overly generous...
- ( laughter )
...introduction.
I'm definitely
not a hero
or noble or anything.
I'm just trying
to do my work
and got into
a little bit of trouble.
( men chanting )
I arrived
in Benghazi in mid-March.
and the night I arrived.
I heard nothing
but bombs and gunfire.
( men whooping )
I wondered.
"What's going on?"
Another journalist said.
"The bombs. that's gelatina.
That's how they fish."
( laughter )
Blow the fish up.
"And the gunfire?
No. that's
celebratory gunfire."
( gunfire )
Jim:
If Gaddafi
comes to Benghazi.
are you guys
prepared to fight?
Diane:
I think in some ways
Libya was
a turning point for Jim.
I was starting to see
his trying to figure out
where he belonged
in the world.
He tried
the Teach for America.
and then Chicago he worked
at the Cook County Jail.
He anguished
over his teaching.
He didn't think he was
a good enough teacher.
He wanted to write
and he loved people
and liked to interact.
tell people's stories.
So when Jim decided
he wanted to go
into journalism
from teaching.
at first we thought
that would be good.
"Maybe that'll be
a better fit. Jim."
But when he decided
to do conflict journalism.
that was a whole
different deal.
Well. he didn't
exactly tell us.
( laughs )
He graduated from Medill
and we said.
"Jim. what are you
going to do?"
And he said.
"Well. I'm working on it."
The next thing we knew.
he was going to go to Iraq
embedded with
the Indiana National Guard.
"Well. I guess
I'm a conflict journalist
at this point."
So that's how we found out.
( gunfire )
Jim:
It's an all-out sprint.
an exhilarating and dangerous
run for cover.
You got him?
John Jr.:
When Jim started
the journalism path.
we did have some heated
discussions on views
and the military
and whatnot.
My views are a little bit
more conservative than Jim's.
I would say
a little bit more liberal.
But when he did his embed.
I think. is where
we came closer together.
Jim:
As soon as the shooting
died down.
the platoon discovered
a body limp on the roof.
Do they know
who the guy is?
Yes.
His family members.
- These are the family?
- Yeah.
John. Jr.:
Then he came back to my house
and he told me--
he was like.
"John. I'm thinking about
going to Libya."
I'm like. "Jim.
that's a horrible idea.
That is absolutely
a horrible idea.
If you go over there.
no one's coming for you.
Why would you put
your life in danger?
We're dropping bombs
over there.
And God forbid
if you go over there
and we accidentally
kill you."
I mean. why?
Why?
( chanting )
Jim:
Libya was very exciting
as a journalist
because you had this chance
to talk directly to people.
to see exactly
what was going on.
( chanting )
There were no
US soldiers anymore.
No organized army
anymore telling you
what you should
and shouldn't do.
( gunshots )
But it was also
extremely dangerous.
- ( shouting )
- ( gunfire )
I was actually talking
to one of my buddies
boasting
about my brother Jim
and how he's
this journalist
and is super crazy.
but badass at the same time.
I was like. "Yeah.
my brother's a badass.
He's crazy.
He's awesome."
I also was
very naive myself.
I didn't know exactly
what that would mean.
I didn't know
he was actually
going to be immersed
in actual crossfire.
- ( gunfire )
- There's snipers
in this building
about one kilometer away.
The group decided to go in.
Heavy fighting.
Heavy casualties.
About 30 wounded.
two dead
as of this morning.
Tom:
There's one video
that always
stands out to me.
It's when he's standing
in the square.
There does seem to be
a strong sense
that they won't
give up the fight.
And that they are a force
of young fighting men.
Although unorganized.
there's plenty of will
to hold out here.
How does my guy
know this stuff?
How does Jim Foley--
he's just my meathead
friend. you know?
It was so foreign to me
in terms of an experience.
I'm like.
"How do you get into Libya?
You're a freelancer?
Who wants this?
Are you getting paid?"
This is Jim Foley
reporting from downtown
Benghazi.
Revolutionary Square.
"Global Post."
Phil:
Jim was there
at the early stage
of this movement
of there being
more freelancers
in conflict areas.
The world
has changed so much
in terms of
digital publishing
and newspapers started
to eliminate things
that they didn't see
as essential.
International
coverage dwindled down
to very little.
so we saw an opportunity
to fill that void
and we needed to work
with freelancers.
Clare:
Freelancers decide
to work together
just on the basis of this
initial quick-read chemistry.
I saw this new guy
who I hadn't met before.
He looked friendly enough.
so I said. "Hey. what's up?"
He said. "Not much.
Going to the frontline."
He's heard
a lot about Libya
and the fact that
it was very cheap to work.
Rebels and protestors
were eager to show us
their side of the story.
They were driving us
all over for free.
They were translating
for us for free.
Many of us never really
experienced the luxury
of journalism
in its heyday.
What we do is journalism
on a shoestring budget.
So we've had to be a lot
more resourceful in a way
and just more street savvy.
I think. in a sense.
the way we all got
to know each other
was the Africa Hotel
in Benghazi.
It was the cheapest hotel.
and the crappiest.
and we were all
staying there.
I'd seen Jim talking
to a few other journalists.
and he was just really
friendly with everybody.
It was unusual
in a place like that.
There's still an edge
of competitiveness
in that environment.
whereas Jim was just like.
"Yeah. whatever."
He gave off a really good
first impression.
and it helps
that he's a super
good-looking guy.
I was just like.
"Who is this guy?
Who are you?"
There wasn't anything mundane
about the man whatsoever.
He never really
projected himself
onto a situation
and he dealt
well with people.
Jim:
Who are the Libyan rebels
determined to overthrow
42 years of dictatorship?
- Offshore welder.
- Platform. yes.
Okay. Dangerous job.
( laughs )
Jim:
They're brave
as individuals.
but many show a dangerous
lack of weapons training.
Clare:
There were so many
freelancers
who came in
at that point in time
who were so new.
Jim and I among them.
and I found out only later
that there were a number
of much more experienced
photojournalists
who had made
one or two trips
to the frontline
and said. "Fuck it.
This is way too dangerous."
( Manu speaking )
Jim had a high tolerance
for danger.
- ( explosion )
- Jim: Shit.
Sure. he was drawn to that.
All of us are. in a way.
He was cool as a cucumber
as well.
wearing this little
tiny vest he used to wear.
Clare:
The fact that
he stayed so calm
made it easy to feel calm
in that situation.
But. of course.
sometimes I was just like.
"That's crazy.
I'm not going there with you."
Jim:
I would come back
to Benghazi
and there was stuff
going on there.
There was families
and they were out there
in the protests.
and they were out
there maybe handling
medical supplies.
which is probably
more important
to what this
revolutionary movement was.
But then being called out
to that frontline again
like some kind of
siren song...
It was one of those mornings
where we decided
we were gonna
get out there early.
We wanted
to get a fresh look
at the frontlines.
It was myself.
Clare Gillis.
Manu Brabo.
and Anton Hammerl.
a South African
photojournalist.
- Meet my friend!
- Anton.
Anton!
Jim:
And what it was. really.
was just a highway.
a coastal highway
going all across Libya.
And this is where
the battle was going on.
So it was kind of like
a Mad Max type war.
This was something common
that some reporters did.
Freelancers like myself
who didn't have big budgets.
we'd jump in
with the rebels.
It was at your own risk
if you wanted to go
further or not.
We got to the point
where we saw another
group of rebels
saying Gaddafi forces
are 300 meters away.
And myself.
looking at Clare.
like.
"That's impossible."
I remember Anton
turning to me
and saying.
"Hey. this isn't safe."
But we didn't turn around.
We said. "Let's get off
the road anyways."
That was the exact
wrong thing to do.
Two heavily armed
Gaddafi pickup trucks
came over
that rise firing.
I remember so clearly
the sound of it.
the volume of it.
the sound of something
heating metal.
And I remember
hoping against hope
that there would be
some kind of out
out of this.
there was some kind
of trapdoor in time.
I crawled back
to the sand dune.
Anton was at
the other sand dune
in front of me.
I heard him call for help.
It appeared he was cut across
the midsection with AK fire.
and there was
a serious amount of blood.
He had already
lost consciousness
and probably already died.
A group of young soldiers
approached me
and we were thrown
in the back of a truck.
I remember
getting photographed
with a cell phone
and thinking
this is where they find
all these photographs
that are evidence
of war crimes someday.
and realizing
this is me now.
Diane:
I was with my mother.
We were out to lunch
and I received a phone call.
And that's how
we first heard. you know?
I think I was in denial
about how dangerous
this really was. Brian.
I was furious.
just furious.
Scared for him.
furious.
I hate to revisit
it. but it was like.
"I told you. Jim."
I think we all
went through the stages
of total shock
and then just.
"What are we going to do?"
And then anger.
After all.
we're family. you know?
Jim:
You're so humbled.
You lost everything--
your freedom.
your control.
your ability
to talk to anybody
and tell anybody
you're okay.
Thinking one minute.
"Oh. yeah.
I'm a foreign
correspondent."
The next minute.
somebody who you
respect killed
and you have nothing.
Clare:
Jim was concerned
that his own
competitiveness
with Manu. with Anton.
with himself.
his own sort of
macho aggressiveness
had driven him
to make decisions
that were not
the best decisions.
We were all questioning
our judgment.
One of the main things
that affected all of us
is that Anton had kids
and none of us do.
Jim:
Every day I have to
deal with the fact
that Anton is not
going to ever see
his three kids anymore.
and I was part of that
decision-making process...
that took him away--
that took him away
from his kids and his wife.
( Manu speaking )
Jim:
I had a lot of time
to play over those moments.
especially that one day
when we were captured.
I tried to question myself.
"What are you reporting on?
What is this all about?"
It was quickly apparent
that this was about
being what you think
is an authentic
conflict correspondent.
seeing the frontline.
and it not being enough
to just see it
from a distance.
but to push it
to the next level.
You were basically
waiting to get shelled.
and the question is.
"Why?"
You know.
"Why are you doing this?"
Michael:
A lot of us were just
scratching our head. right?
There's no money.
Maybe you get a story
here and there
that you sell.
I used to loan him money.
My credit report
has one ding on it.
and it's the one loan
that I cosigned with Jim.
I think Jimmy was just
a little outside the lines.
He was wicked disorganized.
Mark:
We had to tell him
to come to dinner.
If dinner was at 5:00.
we'd tell him it was at 3:00.
so he'd show up at 5:00.
He always lives
in the moment.
I don't know
if Mike ever told you
that Jim was late
to his wedding.
"John. can I sleep
at your house?
John. can my friend
stay at your house?"
"Yes. Jim. yes."
Even though you were like.
"Jim. just wake up!
Wake up!
What are you doing?
Get a real job.
Start saving up
for retirement."
I remember I said. "Why don't
you come to Chicago?
My dad runs this boot camp
that's teaching
young felons."
He goes there
for the interview
and I call him afterwards
and I'm like.
"How'd the interview go?"
He's like. "It was great.
I think it went great."
I call my dad and he goes.
"He said it went great.
did he?
Because I just talked to
the lady at the hiring board.
and when she went out there.
she found Jim sleeping
with his head
back on the wall
and he's wearing jeans
with paint or something
all over them."
I call Jim back.
I'm like. "Jim.
what the hell happened
at the interview?"
He's like.
"It was hot in there. Tom.
It was hot.
I just put my head back
and I nodded off."
I'm like.
"Did you have jeans on
with paint?"
And he's like.
"Yeah. they had these
symbols on them.
What was I supposed to wear?"
I'm like. "Jim. it's
an interview.
It's an interview.
You can't do this."
So my dad
always says that Jim had
a million-dollar resume
and a 10-cent interview.
He came
and he started teaching
reading and writing.
some literature.
and he was really good
with these kids.
because Jim was into
hip-hop and rap
and he liked
to grab a mic himself.
Jim connected
with these guys.
He'd find out
about their backgrounds.
talk to them.
I think that
really hit him.
He was seeing young guys
that came from
terrible neighborhoods
that never really
had a chance.
I think he started seeing
there are people who need
their stories told.
Jim:
The prison that we were
transferred to
was filled with all
these political prisoners
from all walks of life.
Some were fishermen.
some were engineers.
It was the warmth
of these Libyans that said.
"Here you're our guest.
Take this bed.
You don't have a cigarette?
Here's a cigarette."
"You want an extra piece
of chicken? Here."
These guys understand
that I'm a journalist
and I'm trying
to get the truth.
and perhaps wrongly
they think I'm on their side.
but I certainly
feel like it now.
( chanting over P.A. )
You know that if you
are kind of without hope.
you're totally humbled.
you tend to go to your faith
if you have faith.
Praying five times a day--
it was the life.
It was their only source
of life in prison.
I was up nights
talking to them.
Eventually. one of them said.
"Why don't you pray with us?"
And I said.
"No. I'll pray to Isa.
I pray to Jesus
when you guys are praying."
He sort of looked at me
like. "Okay."
I guess
I'm an experiential person.
so I started
praying with them.
Little did I know.
I just proclaimed my
conversion to Islam.
( laughter )
So from then on out.
I prayed with them
five times a day.
And it was just--
it was so powerful.
and it was something
that I needed to do.
But it was difficult.
I was thinking.
"Jesus. am I praying to Allah?
Am I violating
my belief in you?"
I don't have
an answer to that.
I just know
that I was authentically
praying with them
and I was authentically
also praying to Jesus.
Michael:
Jim and I were
very close in age.
look enough alike that
I used his ID in college.
but that's about it.
We couldn't be
more different.
Jim was really different
from most of us. right?
I mean. to do
what he went on to do.
it's not a normal path.
When Jim was taken
in Libya.
I just went into
overdrive at that point.
It's a nightmare.
Each day it becomes harder
with the lack
of information.
We know he's in Tripoli.
We believe he's in
a detention center.
We really don't know
much more beyond that.
We organized this huge group
of Jimmy's friends.
We called them FOJs--
friends of Jim.
We had a lot
of outside help.
but Michael was sort of
the CEO of the group.
His statement was
there are no measurables
other than getting
Jim home.
Our biggest fear
is that it becomes
yesterday's story
and people
forget about it.
We love Jim
and we miss him.
We want him home.
Brian:
Tell me about the release.
What was that day like
for you guys?
Reporter:
After successful
diplomatic negotiations.
two American journalists
and a Spanish journalist
are finally going home
after being kidnapped
and detained
by the Libyan government
forces for 44 days.
- What is your name?
- Manu Brabo.
- Were you okay?
Were you looked after?
- I'm fine.
If you didn't catch
it the first time around.
get it from your buddy.
Guys. could you please
give them some space?
Michael:
What was really interesting
about that whole process.
there was a day
where we were making
some progress
and I just decided
that I have to go.
I have to get on
a plane and go.
I don't know.
I can't describe it.
But I knew--
at least felt strongly--
that it was going to
work out.
All the security guys
wanted to debrief him first.
and finally I said.
"Enough of this shit"
and just went into
the hotel room.
I remember seeing Jim.
he had a full beard.
and he just grabbed me
and said. "Mike."
We both kind of just
grabbed each other's arms.
like. just to--
is it real?
I ordered pizza
and as many Heinekens
as they could put in a car
and about two packs
of cigarettes
because I knew that's all
they had over there.
I looked at them and I said.
"I guess I got this one."
and we just stayed up
all night.
Katie:
All the family
and friends.
we're all together
waiting for them.
And all of a sudden we see
these blue lights
just rushing at us.
( sirens blaring )
We're like.
"Oh. my God. this is Jim.
This is--
he's actually here."
I don't know.
it was like a movie.
He was so happy
to see everybody.
Jim:
You have a close call.
That's pure luck
that you didn't get
killed there.
It's not worth seeing your
mother or father bawling
and worrying about
your grandmother dying
because you're in prison.
It's not worth these things.
And outside.
in my parents' home
in a comfortable house
in New Hampshire.
I sort of had
to start processing.
I was horrified to learn
how much
my friends and family
had done to help me.
I was inspired
and I was horrified.
It was a weird feeling of.
like. going to your own funeral.
There's no going back
from something like this.
Some of the things
I'll never be able to change.
but I wish--
I wish that I could.
- This is--
- What are you gonna do?
This is Jim's blazer from
when he spoke at Marquette.
this brown one.
Bunch of stuff
to go through.
Yeah. so Jim lived with us
for. what. three months?
Summer after he was
released from Libya.
Summer until-- yeah.
up until he went back.
Used to have all
his clothes in here.
You can still see
his CamelBak from
the field.
- Sleeping bags.
- All his sleeping bags.
Yeah.
That was his bed
right there.
He'd always
crash out there.
So it was cool
having Jim here.
especially after him
having been gone in Libya.
because I think
when he came back.
you just wanted
to touch him a lot.
Because. I don't know.
for me it was like. poke.
and just make sure
he's real.
It was almost--
you're just
more appreciative of him.
especially with the kids
getting to have him here
because he was
always on the go.
They loved their Uncle Jim.
They'd come downstairs
at the crack of dawn
and wake him up.
It was good
as much as it--
I think he had an itch
he couldn't scratch
when he was domesticated.
Phil:
When Jim came back
from Libya.
I offered him
a full-time job here
as an editor.
while he sorted out
what he would do next.
He sat right outside
my office.
He was grateful
to have the job.
but working in an office
was clearly not
what he liked the most.
He was quiet.
I don't want to say
he was withdrawn.
but he was quiet.
Katie:
And I just remember Brad--
my fiancé-- and Jim
were in the basement.
and Brad doesn't
even remember a time
where Jim was sleeping.
After the family
had kind of settled down.
Jim just went
right to business.
right to work.
Diane:
We had found him a very good
psychologist to talk to.
but he seemed so well.
if you will.
that we didn't push it.
But he was so restless
here at home.
He didn't want to
be here at home.
Jim:
Feeling like you
survived something.
it has a strange
sort of force
that you are
drawn back to.
I think that's
the absolute reality.
Zac:
Everything else
becomes foreign.
It was strange coming back
to the real world.
It was weird.
It was normal in there.
Clare:
Yeah. if I go to Wal-Mart
and I'm looking at
literally an entire aisle
full of Tupperware.
it boggles my mind.
There's a deep absurdity
to understanding the peace
that we're lucky enough
to have in this country
and the questions
that it raises
about how do
we make our money.
what is the basis
of our peace.
of our economic viability.
of the fact that I can look
at all of this Tupperware
and someone else
somewhere else
is looking at
the ruins of their home.
Zac:
You start missing
all the bombs
and the fighting
and everything.
I just used to love
sitting up at night
and just listening.
( gunfire )
It's really kind of sick.
- ( explosions )
- But it also--
it feels super fortunate
for being there.
You think. like.
out of 25 million people
in your country.
you're the only person
who's got to experience that.
Like. fuck. man.
how fortunate am I?
You're witnessing
history unfolding
and you're getting
this perspective
that is so unique.
( Manu speaking )
I believe that frontline
journalism is important.
Without these photos
and videos
and firsthand experience.
we can't really
tell the world
how bad it might be.
( singing in Arabic )
( explosion )
Woman:
James Foley
joins us now live
from inside northern Syria
with more on what he saw.
Tell us more about what
you were able to witness.
Yes. thank you.
You've heard about
indiscriminate shelling.
but to see
those bodies left over
from a direct mortar hit
was really shocking.
These were civilians.
and they are under pretty
continuous shelling.
( chanting )
Thank you.
It seemed like
he started thinking
about going to Syria.
and by the time
he mentioned it.
it was like he'd already
kind of made up his mind.
And he said he was going
with John Cantlie.
who's another colleague--
a British photojournalist
that we'd all met
in Libya the year before.
- Man: What's your name?
- Jim.
- John. Jim and John.
- Man: John. Jim.
Johnny. you say I love you.
You say.
Diane:
I don't know.
I really didn't
really get
into it with Jim.
I think I made it
too easy for him.
I mean. it was something
he wanted to do.
and so we were
trying to be supportive
about his decision
to do that. you know?
You just want to
punch him in the face.
You know. in a loving.
brotherly way.
But you're like.
"Come on. Jim! Come on!"
Tom:
The last conversation I ever
had with Jim. I said to him.
"Jim. man.
why do you keep going
back into Syria?
I mean. what's it like?"
And he's like.
"It's crazy. it's crazy."
I'm like "Well. is it more
dangerous than Libya?"
He's like. "Yeah. it's more
dangerous than Libya!"
I'm like.
"You got captured in Libya!"
You couldn't
talk him out of it.
( chanting )
Jim: You know.
the thing is. is there's
physical courage. right?
For some reason.
I have physical courage.
But really. think about it.
that's nothing
compared to moral courage.
I can go
and get those shots.
but if I don't have
the moral courage
to challenge authority.
to write about things
that are going to maybe have
reprisals on my career--
if I don't have moral courage.
we don't have journalism.
Jim chose one story
in particular about
this hospital.
the Dar Al Shifa
Hospital in Aleppo.
It was actually
Jim's idea to spend
a week in that hospital
documenting what the doctors
and the staff there
were doing
on a daily basis.
Yes.
- Whew!
- ( man shouts )
( chanting )
Nicole:
From what he
and I witnessed.
they were literally
shuttling people with drips
and bandages
and everything
in these tiny
little taxis and cars.
And Jim was the one
who came up with the idea
of raising money
to get an ambulance
for the hospital.
And he was in touch
with everybody.
and there was
an ambulance
that was
a secondhand ambulance
that was coming
from Austria.
and Jim and I actually
made one trip in
and we saw the ambulance
sitting outside the hospital.
And that moment of joy
on his face was priceless.
He was just like.
"It made it. It's awesome."
Clare:
I would say the flip side
of his willingness
to get out there
and do things
is that like.
okay. so you get
an ambulance into Syria.
Some militia is
going to commandeer it
and use it
for their own purposes.
They're going to
put an anti-aircraft
in the back of it.
like. go blow shit up.
Jim was not focused
on that kind of issue.
He would think about what's
the best-case scenario.
not how things
could go wrong.
Nicole:
It becomes very personal
because we have to live
amongst the local population.
and it's such this brutal.
endless conflict
that you just--
you feel so kind of alone
in the sense
that you can't do
anything about it.
You can't do anything
for these people--
for the people
you've made friends with
and for the people
who took you in
and shared
their food with you
and wanted you to
play with their children.
We'd become the intimate
chroniclers of this conflict.
We don't have bureaus
to go back to.
You're there.
and every moment of it
you share with the locals.
And I think there was
just this enormous guilt
that rode on Jim's back
that made him
feel so compelled
to do much more
than just record video
and file it.
There were times where he was
offering up video for free
and I would chastise
him for it. I'd be like.
"What are you doing?"
He was like. "Nah. whatever.
It's fine. It's all good.
I just want to make sure
the video gets out there."
Diane:
Jim's the kind of guy
who never needed much.
Some of the lifestyle
of a conflict journalist
is tough.
but that didn't bother Jim.
The only possessions
I think Jim cared about
were books and CDs.
I mean his camera.
ultimately.
He'd come home
without a toothbrush.
Just use whatever
toothbrush was available.
Jim could fall asleep
anywhere.
All he needed
was just a little space
on the floor.
He was like a cat.
Brian:
This is a good one.
( Manu speaking )
Diane:
Over time. you know.
he slowly got rid
of his apartment.
sold his car.
He just ended up
really owning nothing.
So. what would
he want for Christmas?
This last time
before going to Syria.
he wanted a tough
pair of pants.
He really did
have less and less
and it didn't
bother him at all
because he seemed
richer and richer.
Nicole:
There was one day
in August
when a Syrian activist
was taking us around
this neighborhood
called Bustan al-Qasr
and this fighter jet
just started circling above
and just swooped right down
and hit a building
that was a couple hundred
feet from us.
- ( gunfire )
- ( explosions )
We started seeing
civilians coming out
and just clutching
nothing. really.
Just ashen faces.
There was rubble everywhere.
It was chaos.
( shouting )
And the plane
came around again.
It dropped another bomb
really close by.
and. actually.
we were right across
the building.
and we looked up
and we could see
the rubble start
coming down.
That bomb had hit
a family of seven.
( speaking Arabic )
Jim:
Who was killed?
Who?
Nicole:
It was horrific in
the scale of it.
but also just--
I think nothing prepares you
for seeing kids being killed
and maimed in that way.
and I know that Jim
really loves kids.
So. you know.
we were both just--
we didn't say
anything until we got
to the field hospital
where they were
bringing the bodies.
And we were both
just in this mode
of just needing to get
the pictures out.
I think when
we were finished
that night. though.
we kind of sat down
and lit a cigarette
and we just started
talking about it.
Really. there wasn't
very much to say. though.
You know. like.
what is there to talk about
when you witness
something like that?
So we just sort of
sat in silence.
Zac:
Nothing prepares
you for that.
No amount of courses.
Nothing.
You just go there
and you'll either handle it
or you don't.
and that's cool.
Either you run
or you stay.
And there's--
not one is better
than the other.
but just don't
delude yourself.
Some people aren't
meant for that.
Clare:
The shine was starting
to come off in a way.
There was a period of time
where journalists
were welcomed with open arms
because they'd seen
what had happened in Libya.
And when that didn't
come about after a year.
after a year and a half.
after two years.
it's just like. "Okay.
what are you guys doing?"
I had a doctor
tell me at the hospital
that Jim helped raise money
for an ambulance--
he was like. "Look. you guys
are in and out of here
since one year.
and it's the same exact thing
except it's worse.
I don't want to
talk to you."
If the populace
on the ground
whose side
you're documenting
is getting
more uneasy with you
or less willing to help--
you're very dependent
on the goodwill
of the people
you're around.
( Manu speaking )
It's just that moment of.
like. how well can you
know anybody?
Even. say you know
someone very well.
two years of war.
three years of war.
that's going
to change anybody.
They warned journalists.
They were like.
"Al-Qaeda is coming."
Maybe even worse
than al-Qaeda is coming
and nobody is going to help us
against the Assad regime
except for these guys.
So it was all there.
Clare:
One of the main things
I noticed
the last time
when he came out.
he looked really hollow
and he was quite--
quite silent.
He had that amazing
room-brightening smile
even if he had seen
terrible things. as one does.
It was disheartening
to see.
Mark:
Before he left for Syria.
I think we made it a point.
we were going to bring him down
to the Faneuil Hall district
and go to the comedy club
down there.
The comedians
were horrible.
but I was in
the mood to laugh.
so I'm just
laughing at anything.
And I just remember
looking at Jim
and he was just
dead-faced.
And then me and Jim
went outside for a cigarette
like we always do.
He said he had to go.
We had a long hug.
I remember I hugged him
a really long time.
Just hugged him
really tight.
I said be careful.
Obviously. I didn't feel
like that was the last time
I was going to see him.
but it was a good night.
It was a good end
of the night. you know?
John. Sr.:
I guess if I had
any regrets. Brian.
I regret that
I found it difficult
to communicate with Jim.
I don't know
if it's the male thing
or whatever it is.
but I just wish
I was able to share more
of who I was
with Jim again
and get him to share
who he was with me.
which might have been
just as difficult. you know?
Diane:
He would interview us
when we came home
and he did a great job
interviewing us.
because you felt like talking
because he was listening.
He wanted to know
how we were.
And that was--
when he came home.
that's what
he wanted to know.
He wanted.
"Well. how are you?
How you doing?"
"How's Grandma?
How's Katie and Mark?"
And he just
wanted to know how
everyone was doing.
So in that way.
Jim was kind of solitary.
Kristie:
He was home.
end of October.
right before he went back
to Syria that last time.
and he was going--
I remember
he was leaving here
and he was going to
New York to get a helmet
from somebody.
which was good.
We were like.
"Getting safety equipment.
We like this."
Yeah. I remember we left
and we dropped him off
at a train station.
And he-- we were going
to see him in December.
- He was supposed to
come home kind of--
- You have a good memory.
He was supposed to
come home mid-December.
And we were like.
"Be safe. See you soon."
And unfortunately.
that didn't--
Yeah.
- Sorry.
- It's okay.
Nicole:
We'd spent the beginning
of November in Aleppo again
with Jim. John Cantlie.
and Mustafa. our translator.
who's become
a friend of ours.
I had had some issues
with my camera that week.
So. I was like. "Jim. I got
to go back to Istanbul.
I'll see you guys
in a week."
The moment when
I said bye to Jim.
I had this feeling
of reluctance to leave.
I think in a way
maybe it did upset
the balance
that he and I
had shared for so long.
There are superstitions
when you're in a war zone.
There's like this one thing
that he and I shared.
which was our
lucky lighter.
It's very common
in the Middle East.
It's like the evil eye
to ward off evil spirits.
We'd used it
for everything.
and for some reason it never
ran out of lighter fluid.
It's just this stupid idea.
You put your hopes into one
object to make it feel safe.
I think about it
a lot afterwards.
that he didn't
have it with him.
Maybe if I just gave him
the lucky lighter.
everything might have
turned out okay.
I don't know.
That day.
I was in Reyhanli.
which is the border town.
and I would have
seen him at about 5:00.
So I checked in
and I told Jim.
I'm like.
"Hey. I'm here.
so text me
when you get in."
5:00 rolls by.
and I started to worry.
7:00.
8:00 rolls around.
and I'm like.
"Something is really wrong."
So I called Mustafa.
and the first thing
he said to me was.
"Nicole. I'm so sorry.
I didn't--
I couldn't do anything."
I was like.
"What are you talking about?
What happened?"
He was like.
"We were coming.
We were in the taxi.
We were coming
to Turkey to meet you.
and this van with
these four guys with guns.
they stopped us
on the road
and they told us
to get out.
And they were pointing
their guns at us
and screaming."
The gunman made Mustafa
tie up their hands.
and they put John and Jim
into the back of their van.
So. I hung up
and I just started crying.
I was like--
I didn't know if I was
gonna see Jim again.
and that was the first thought
that came to my head.
John. Sr.:
It was almost surreal.
This is a bad dream.
It's not really happening.
It's not happening.
This can't be--
this can't happen again.
We can't do this again.
Yeah. it was--
I dove in just like before.
I felt like.
"Okay. it's going to be 45
to 100 days of hell.
and then
we'll have him back."
In a matter of a week.
you could tell it was
very different.
A lot of misinformation.
as opposed to last time
in Libya--
after a week went by
we knew where he was.
who to deal with.
so we just concentrated on
routes to get to one person.
Here was a mystery
right out of a crime show
or something
where you're trying
to piece together bits
of information.
Nicole:
For the next three weeks.
there was just dead ends
and false information
and rumors and people
being scared of talking
because they had a suspicion
of who maybe was responsible
and they didn't want to
get entangled in it.
Diane:
Phil Balboni offered
to stand up
a security team
to try to find Jim.
So. all these people
were trying so hard
to get in place.
but it was a very.
very chaotic.
confusing time.
John. Jr.:
You're on eggshells.
You're just waiting to hear.
It's exhausting.
and I know Jim felt
guilty for that.
and I'm not trying to
make him feel more guilty.
but it's just a toll
that's taken
by the families.
Brian:
What were the hurdles
getting the White House
and FBI involved?
Michael:
It was very tough
to get action.
And I understand that
the world is a big place.
and so I actually
felt guilty sometimes
trying not to ask
too much of them.
Jim made this decision.
but just give it
your best attention
and we'll trust you.
That's kind of
where it started.
the relationship.
Then I met the first agent
that came over
and it was just a kid
out of school.
and his first question
to me was had I asked
the regime for assistance.
Are you
fucking kidding me?
Have I called the regime
and asked them for assistance?
No. I hadn't thought of that.
Thank you.
Thank you very much
for that tip.
They told us--
they advised us
to be quiet.
because hopefully
they could find him
and get him out and such.
So we didn't say anything.
We went through
Christmas and all that
not telling anyone
but our closest family
that Jim was missing.
Tom:
In some ways
it was better
because I didn't
have to explain it.
Because at times
it could feel accusatory.
like. "Well. he was
in Syria."
That's not fair.
You don't do that
with police or firemen
or something like that
who do dangerous jobs.
You don't say.
"Well. you were in a fire.
What did you think
would happen?"
My friend doesn't need
to explain why he's
a journalist.
Diane:
Come the new year.
I couldn't stand it.
I was frantic.
So we chose to go public.
John. Sr.:
I appeal to the people
who have Jim
to give us some information
in terms of his welfare.
his health.
Diane:
It breaks my heart
that the persons
who have captured him
don't understand
his goodness.
My personal feeling is that
silence helps two people.
One is the government--
it doesn't push them
to do more sooner--
and the captors.
It allows them to do
whatever they want.
It's difficult now
with all the talk
about the Islamic State.
They've become
so famous or infamous.
But the Islamic State.
ISIS. ISIL.
was on nobody's
radar at the time.
With a very high
degree of confidence.
we now believe
that Jim was abducted
by a pro-government
militia group
and was subsequently
turned over
to Syrian
government forces.
This is the first time
we've really heard
anything like this.
so we are very hopeful.
like John says.
Well. it turned out
we were dead wrong about that.
Michael:
All the information up front
was just a bunch of BS.
No one knew what the heck
they were talking about
because we had no access.
That whole year.
I don't care what anyone says.
all the efforts.
all the leads.
all this and that...
we were in the wrong area
of the country. you know?
Syria is about the size
of New England. maybe?
A little smaller.
So here you go. Brian.
Go into New England.
Find Jim.
I think the moment
that I learned that he had
been kidnapped.
I was just like.
this is going to be
a really long process.
But I'm going
to do anything
that I can in my power
to get him home.
Because I can't stand
the thought of him
being in a cell somewhere
cold and hungry.
And I can't sit here
and not try
to look for him.
Daniel:
My name is Daniel.
and I'm a Danish
photojournalist.
I started as a gymnast.
and while I spent
all my time in gyms
all around the world
doing gymnastics.
I got bored when I didn't do
anything else
and I started to
take pictures.
I only planned to be inside
Syria for two days.
I had one day of work
when I walked around
this small quiet town.
It was spring.
so the weather
started to be very better.
and people seemed
happy and relaxed
and we were told
to go and speak
to some guys in the area.
Very calmly.
we're sitting on sofas.
They were offering tea.
Everything
was calm and quiet.
even though I knew that
something was strange.
something was wrong.
And then they
asked me to stand up
and they took off
my glasses.
and they just-- "Don't worry.
this is just a procedure."
That was how
everything began.
So. you know.
a quiet Sunday
beautiful spring morning
became a nightmare for me.
The longer
you are a hostage.
the easier
it becomes in some way.
the better you get at it.
And I had. like.
I think. one.
one and half months
by myself.
After. I believe.
two and a half months.
I was put together
with two other Westerners.
And then we were
put together four.
I think we were
five together.
and then seven together.
And then came
another one-- eight.
Then it just started
to evolve.
We were in that cell--
British. Americans.
French. Italian. German.
Danish. Russian. Spanish.
We were 19 at one stage.
One day we had to sit
faces to the wall.
but I could see
under my arms.
I could see some
mattresses were moved in.
and there came some guys
in traditional Syrian clothes.
And then they
closed the door again.
the big metal door.
and I looked up.
and there was James
and John Cantlie.
Everybody was like.
"Yay! Welcome! Welcome!
Welcome!"
It's two new friends.
( Pierre speaking )
I created this
picture in my head
of this big war
journalist.
and so I could only get
disappointed in a way.
But I remember
him being like...
"What's happening?"
So that was basically
the first time I met him.
But it was real different
to be put together
with James and John.
because they've been together
in prison for almost a year.
When I first saw them.
they were the most
experienced of us.
and I started
from the beginning.
I think the whole group
started to lean a little
bit against them.
( Pierre speaking )
Daniel:
James was very silent
most of the time.
He was very good
at listening.
He managed to make
the room bigger in a way
by being small himself.
and that is a very.
very difficult thing to be.
And you really
want to scream in the head
of everybody like.
"Fuck off!"
( Nicolas speaking )
( Didier speaking )
Daniel:
I remember one time.
James was asked
to stand up the whole night
in the middle of the room.
( Pierre speaking )
( Didier speaking )
Daniel:
Late at night.
there was no light at all.
so we were just sitting there
in complete darkness.
and that time really.
really. really went slowly.
What we did.
James and I.
we started
to develop a way
of passing through
these hours of darkness
by giving each other.
like. massages.
And it sounds maybe
a little bit. you know.
strange or gay
or whatever.
but there was something--
there was something
nice about it.
And James asked me.
"Can you teach me
how to give
a real nice massage.
so when I get out
and I meet a woman. I can--
I can really impress her?"
So we started having
these kind of lessons.
Our bodies had witnessed
a lot of trauma
and the fact that somebody
is actually touching you
and it's a nice feeling.
for me.
it was a nice way
to feel a little bit
human again.
And James. he never learned
how to give a proper massage.
It was awful every time.
So. he really--
he really managed
to get a good deal
out of that one.
( Pierre speaking )
( Nicolas speaking )
Daniel:
I remember one time.
we were given
a lot of dates to eat.
And at some point
we were moved.
and you just don't
leave food behind
or destroy it or whatever.
but sometimes
you have to do it
because there's
nowhere to put it.
( Nicolas speaking )
James. he just
took out his pants
and he took out
two kilos of dates.
"Don't worry. guys."
He could have taken
all the food by himself
later that night
or whatever.
but he always
took the things
so he could share
it around
or give it to the people
who didn't have it.
( Nicolas speaking )
Daniel:
In the beginning of James
and John's captivity.
they were really starved.
They didn't like
to talk about it.
They didn't find it
very interesting
to talk about.
But one thing
I know was that...
they really. really.
really had a difficult time.
But they managed
to get back on track
to gain strength again.
It was very
interesting to see
what happened
between James and John.
because they've been
together for almost a year
when I first saw them.
That meant
they had spoken about
every single thing
there is to talk about.
So I was basically the one
starting to listen
to all James' stories again.
There was a period
of time in the prison
where we were
not interrupted
by the guards very often.
That meant that
we could get a routine.
So we worked out.
we did trivia.
we had lectures.
and stuff like this.
We managed after.
I don't know. three weeks.
one month or so.
to make this Risk game.
( Nicolas speaking )
We had a small bucket
that we received
some yogurt in.
and we cut out
a piece of cardboard
and we made three lines.
and we put it in
the bottom of the bucket
and then you should
hold up a date seed
and let it go.
It would fall down.
and whatever
number it landed on.
it would be that number.
So that was our dice
for the game.
( Pierre speaking )
Daniel:
Take 10 journalists. war.
put them into one room
and make them play
the game about taking
control over the world.
It's basically like putting
gasoline to a bonfire.
Daniel:
We started to have
our own small world.
That made
everything much easier
to survive in a way.
It was much easier
to understand.
We didn't have to think
about economy.
about bank loans
or the prices of gas
at the moment.
You adapt
into the situation.
and then suddenly
this whole thing
becomes a part
of your life.
This is your life.
When you look back on it.
that's what I remember.
was our small society
where we really start
to know each other.
You know
who made this fart.
You could smell--
"This is the fart of you."
( Nicolas speaking )
Daniel:
I remember James'
40-year-old birthday.
It was late at night.
It was completely dark.
James just--
"Oh. by the way.
I turn 40 today."
I was just like. "What?"
So we sang
a song for him
and I remember
that we said
we hoped it would
be a much better
birthday next year.
( overlapping chatter )
Right here.
One. two. and three.
Come on!
Smile! Please!
Nine! Good!
Jim:
We've been through
a lot together.
Michael has cosigned
loans for me.
( laughter )
He has lent me
his professional clothes.
his car.
his dental plan.
I think sometimes
we struggle to understand
each other
and where exactly
we're coming from
and why we do
the things we do.
Michael has entirely
too much common sense
and sometimes I have entirely
too little common sense.
We've somehow grown closer
despite the differences.
and it's-- I guess
it's about being brothers.
Michael:
I'd say the first 100.
150 days I was all in.
but I definitely retracted
pretty strongly after that.
I have a lot of regrets about
not continuing full steam.
and I don't know
if it was because
I was trying
to protect myself
or I was just trying
to protect my family
and give the kids
the attention I have.
I could argue that that's
what Jim would prefer.
and I don't know--
it was all kinds of
excuses or reasons.
but it's something
I do feel terrible about.
But then I got pulled
right back into it
very strongly
and very immediately
when the first e-mail
came to me.
"Hello. we have James
and want to
negotiate for him.
He is safe.
He is our friend
and we do not want
to hurt him.
If you want cooperation.
we have rules.
You cannot go
to the media ever
about this.
If you do.
we will not negotiate.
We want money fast."
We shared everything
we had with everybody.
FBI knew.
security team knew--
everyone knew.
They said.
"Just keep them talking."
and all that.
"They're just beginning
their negotiations.
We've got time.
Just keep at it."
Michael:
So. I. after coordinating
with some officials.
replied to them.
"We've been concerned
about Jim
and want to know
that he's okay.
Please provide us with proof
that you have Jim.
and we will be happy
to work things out with you."
Diane:
We still didn't know
who was holding him.
It was obvious
that they were people
against the Assad regime.
but they didn't
identify themselves
any more
than that at all.
They were very shrewd.
And their e-mails.
unfortunately.
were totally
undetectable.
About a week goes by
and they responded.
"James Wright Foley
is being detained by us.
At this stage. no video
or picture evidence
of his well-being
will be provided
until we see tangible progress
in your efforts to negotiate.
However. you will be allowed
to ask three questions
of a personal nature
that nobody except James
will know the answers to.
And our primary demand is that
you use your influence
to pressure
your government
to release
our Muslim prisoners
who they have imprisoned.
whether innocent
or 'guilty' according
to 'your laws.'
If this fails
to bear any fruits.
then our secondary demand
is the sum
of a hundred million euros."
FBI seemed to have
their hands tied
because all
they were able to do
was okay
our family e-mails.
and they really were unable
to help us much with strategy.
They just told us to be
yourselves. be family.
Tell them the truth
is we can't release
any prisoners.
We certainly don't have
a hundred million euro.
Michael came up
with some questions
I didn't know
the answers to.
but we sent those back
to the captors.
Michael:
Then there was some
brief comment.
It says.
"James was detained
whilst operating
as a 'journalist.'
After his capture
and following interrogations.
we came to learn
that he had been embedded
with US troops
serving in Afghanistan
and that his brother
Michael Patrick Foley
is a serving officer
in the US Air Force."
But I was never
in the Air Force.
That was John.
My brother Jim
said that Mike
was the Air Force
officer.
It may have been a typo.
it may not have been.
But I believe
it was my big brother
trying to protect me.
You love
your brothers. but--
but for him to put--
be willing to put
his life on the line
or his body
on the line...
for my protection
is significant.
( Didier speaking )
And. I mean. it's...
Daniel:
I think they came in with
the proof of life for John
and then everybody else
got their proof of lives.
Everybody came in
like. "Yes!"
And we're happy and--
but James didn't get
his proof of life.
Until one day
that they came in
and they asked
James to follow.
And when he came back.
you know.
he came with his arms
over his head.
he said that this was
the best day of his life.
And then him and John.
they hugged each other
and they were
dancing around
like they just won
the big lottery.
Diane:
That was early
December of 2013.
All the answers
came back right on.
We knew they had Jim.
But by the end of December
they e-mailed us
back and said.
"This is the last e-mail
you'll get from us"
and cut off
communication.
John. Sr.:
The first year.
we just trusted
that the government
would have this in hand
and despite our lack
of information. et cetera.
they had been
through this before
and they knew what to do.
and we were in good hands.
At the end of that year.
we realized that nothing
was being done
and that we were really
going to have to do
something on our own.
Phil:
Diane was great
about meeting
with ambassadors
in Washington
from other countries
that might have
some influence.
It turned out that
no one had any influence.
because the group
that had him
didn't listen to anybody.
but we didn't know that.
Man:
It's kind of come as
a surprise to a lot of us.
this group ISIS.
a group that we hadn't
really heard much about.
Who exactly are they?
Woman:
Well. It's a criminal
marauding gang.
They come out
of the original.
very brutal
Iraqi terror group.
Michael:
They're the worst.
They're the worst
of the worst.
Washington doesn't know
how to deal with them.
How's this family
in New England
going to figure
that out. right?
I mean you're dealing
with pure evil.
but a capable
and organized group.
( Pierre speaking )
Daniel:
They were very tough
towards me. also.
But no matter what.
they meant freedom for me.
because they were the ones
negotiating for me.
But James and John
were destroyed
by the Beatles
in the beginning.
Pierre:
He had this ability
to escape the situation.
To enjoy. you know.
the sound of children
playing outside.
Or enjoyed the view
of just some sun
entering through
the window.
( Didier speaking )
( man chanting )
Daniel:
James converted
in the beginning
of his captivity.
And I know that
was at the same period
as he were getting
really bad treatment.
It gave a good routine.
Normally. we have a tradition
of going into church
every Sunday.
But if you cannot do that.
you need another way
of feeling
that you are doing
something with your faith.
You can call it
a surviving skill.
just a way
of being interested
in another culture.
What James used
to say to me
was that for him
God is the same.
( Nicolas speaking )
Diane:
We had such
great Christmases
when the kids were little.
Just wonderful.
wonderful Christmases.
And. you know.
as they got older
and Jim's
siblings married.
they weren't always
able to be home.
But Jim was always home.
Most of my memories of Jim
culminate around the holidays.
You know. the playing
of the video games.
the board games.
the Ping-Pong tournaments.
the anything tournaments.
( overlapping chatter )
John. Jr.:
And you wake up
and you open the gifts.
and you're like.
"Crap. Jim has my name.
What's he going to
give me?"
( laughing )
I shouldn't say that.
It was good times.
And then the last
Christmas he was home.
I remember him
rolling on the floor
with Michael's son Matty.
He loved that kid.
There's a million
Christmas stories. though.
Daniel:
It's difficult for us
to celebrate Christmas
in any way.
We didn't have any presents
to give each other.
So. we decided
to sit down in a circle.
and then we had to say
something nice to each other.
And I remember that
I said to James that.
"James. the first time
I met you was.
you know.
in this prison.
and you looked
as confused
as if you were just
dumped down on the Earth
from the moon
or something.
And you basically
destroyed my whole idea
of this great war journalist
James Wright Foley.
And then suddenly I find out
that you are very clumsy.
you're very bad at sports.
But then again. you--
you're the most--"
I think I said to him.
"You're the most
honest person.
There is no evil at all
to find in you. James.
You are pure good.
Sometimes too good.
And I'm really happy
that I've met you."
That was
our Christmas night.
When I went to bed that night.
I really felt that I had
the best Christmas night
in my life.
( door creaks )
( Didier speaking )
( Pierre speaking )
( Nicolas speaking )
Diane:
So that's when I started
to get more frantic.
I mean. I thought there's
got to be some way
to get the French
and the US to talk.
Didier.
This is
my husband John.
Diane:
They were willing to share all
kinds of things about Jim--
personally. how he was.
what they did.
So I was starting
to get all this hope.
And they have
a hostage crisis
unit in Paris
and they were very generous
with their time.
So it was so different than
what I was experiencing.
I was just kind of like.
"Jeez." you know?
Jim and the others--
our other Americans
are as important
as these guys.
aren't they?
And it was the last
night I was in Paris
and I got a phone call
from John.
He said. "Diane.
we got another e-mail
from the captors."
I thought. "Oh. great.
What did they say?"
And that's when they
threatened to kill Jim.
But me.
in my cluelessness.
I was just excited that
they had reached out to us.
We had raised about
$1 million in pledges
and so I was so excited
to hear from them.
because we thought.
"Now we can tell them
we have this money."
I was just so clueless.
Phil:
We knew that paying
a ransom was illegal.
and we also knew that it
wouldn't have stopped us.
The Foleys were prepared
to mortgage their house
and do what needed to be done
to make a payment.
I have a lot
of evolving thoughts
about this whole process
and what
the government didn't do
that it should have done.
I mean. if you just
look at the facts.
there are 15 European
hostages
who are alive
and with their families
and friends
and loved ones today.
I wish we had started
raising money sooner.
I wish we had negotiated.
I wish it had
turned out differently.
Mark: In some sense.
I was okay with the fact
that he got captured.
because I knew
he was doing what
he wanted to do.
And as a good family member
and as a good brother.
I need to understand that.
My mom did a great job
in keeping faith
and working as hard
as she could.
but from the get-go
once it happened.
I kind of felt like
he was already gone.
Daniel:
So after a group
of the other hostages
was released.
the Beatles.
they came back
the day after.
and they--
they beat the shit
out of James and I.
I think it's called
a charley horse.
when you put your knee
into the legs of a person.
They did that
to me and James
while we had to sit
in stress positions.
I don't know
how many they gave us.
but it just continued.
I never tried anything
that hurt so much
in my entire life.
And then they just left.
I was just laying
there crying.
and I couldn't be
in my own body of pure pain.
And James in the other
corner of the room.
I knew he got exactly
the same treatment as me.
but I couldn't hear it.
He just--
I don't know
if he kept it inside
or how he did it.
but only a few minutes
after they left James.
he kind of looked up
and asked me if I was okay.
I was like.
"Shut up. James."
I remember. I said.
"Don't ask me
if I'm okay."
"Don't worry about me.
Worry about yourself."
Yeah. we just laid there
until the pain started
to disappear a bit.
Two or three days after.
they came in again.
This time. the Beatles
just told us that.
"Now. guys.
everything's changed."
And they took all
our food. our games.
most of the blankets.
They started to use
police clubs.
So. every time
we went to the toilet.
we got beatings
with a stick.
We were so scared.
We lost all hope.
No matter what
came through that door.
it was evil.
Those 14 days
before I got released
was the absolute
worst times.
When people started
to get released.
we decided
to send out letters
with the person
who was released.
But James. he didn't.
He didn't want
to bother any of us.
And I remember one day that
I saw that John and James
had been talking
for some time in the corner.
And after that. John.
he came over to me and said.
"Daniel. James. he wants
to ask you something."
"Okay. Okay.
What's up. James?"
And he's like.
"Oh. uh. it's just if--
if you want to carry out
a message or something."
He was very--
he said it fast.
like he didn't
want to bother me.
There's many
ways of dealing with
a situation like this.
And James.
I think one of the reasons
why he remained so strong
was because
he managed to think about
all the good things.
He saw the light
instead of the dark spots.
where a guy like John.
he was much more realistic.
He knew when it was bad.
But I couldn't
bring out the letter.
I was too afraid
after these 14 days.
so I decided
just to memorize it
as fast as I could.
So I started waiting.
I knew they will
come in the morning
to pick me up.
One day went.
Two days went.
And then fourth day.
fifth day.
Shit. man.
Then I woke up there
the sixth day in the morning.
and I couldn't sleep.
I couldn't sleep all night
because I was so afraid
of what if they are
playing a trick on me.
And James.
he walked over to me.
and he sat down
right next to me
and he said.
"Are you okay. Daniel?"
I said. "Yeah."
Then I just couldn't
hold it back.
and I said. "Fuck. man.
I am really. really scared.
I'm really. really. really.
really scared right now.
I don't know what to do.
what to think. I--"
And he said.
"Daniel. calm down.
Calm down.
Everything will be fine.
You are going home.
They will come in
a few hours or tomorrow.
but one thing
is sure. Daniel.
You will go home."
Once again.
it was a real feeling.
because I was
sitting there crying
and making a scene
in front of James.
and I was about to go home
and. James. he didn't have
anything to look forward to.
James. he went back to
his side of the room.
10 minutes after.
they knocked on the door.
they came in
and asked me to put
a blanket over my head
and follow them.
That was
the last time I--
I saw James.
I call on my friends.
family. and loved ones
to rise up
against my real killers.
the US government.
For what will happen to me
is only a result
of their complacency
and criminality.
I wish I had more time.
I wish I could have
the hope of freedom
and seeing my family
once again.
but that ship has sailed.
Michael:
I hadn't heard Jim's voice
in two years.
I guess you can see it
in his neck. in his face--
just this strength
he has at that moment.
And I think of myself.
I'd be calling for
my mother or something.
Just the strength
he had and I--
I wanted to feel
what he felt.
was the reason
I watched it.
I kept getting
messages saying.
"John. are you okay?
John. are you okay about
what your brother said?"
I'm like. "What are you
talking about?"
I call on my brother John.
who is a member
of the US Air Force.
Think about
what you are doing.
the lives you destroy.
including those
of your own family.
Even though he was
reading the script.
he seemed defiant
to the end.
I mean. for sure.
I still have some guilt
regarding me and--
just me and.
unfortunately.
my profession.
but I'm sure that
he endured torture.
Interestingly.
John and I have--
we've argued a lot
about things since that.
but we've been
communicating a lot more.
We've come a lot closer
as a result of it.
I think Jim
would have loved that.
You know Jim
as well as I do.
He wouldn't
have said those things
if there wasn't someone else
that was going to be harmed
as a result of it.
He never cared
about himself.
Katie:
My only thought
when I found out about Jim
was how am I
going to get home?
I had missed
the initial chaos
of when it all happened.
but slowly we all
kind of came together.
We literally chose
the smallest room possible
in our house.
but everybody was just
kind of huddled together.
Jim always found a way
to bring people together.
Always.
Diane:
I really don't think
I came to know
Jim as a man.
as an adult.
I came to know him
through his friends.
It's hard as a mother.
You know. they're always
your children somehow.
And it's hard to see
that they're adults
with their own gifts
and their own way
in the world.
John Jr.:
The day before
his memorial.
I was like. "Shit."
I was like.
"Now I get it.
Now I get it."
Jokingly. I was always like.
you know. "Jim. get a job.
Jim. save for retirement."
What I didn't recognize.
he was really trying
to teach me.
"John. you need to look
outside of yourself.
John. it's not about
physical or monetary things.
It's about how you act.
It's who you teach.
who you mentor.
Who's going
to remember you?
What are they going
to remember about you?"
John. Sr.:
Jimmy was included
in the long line
of journalists
who gave their lives
to tell the truth.
We were just totally humbled
by the fact that
the committee in Bayeux
would nominate him
to be included
on one of the markers
with 2.000 other deceased
journalists.
It was a very
important moment.
This was Jim.
and it made me
feel very warm inside
that he was accepted
as one of them.
( Didier speaking )
John. Sr.:
And that's the difference
with Jim.
He was just
a you and a me--
a friendly guy--
until tested.
Where that came from--
I don't know. Brian.
Because you just can't grit
something like that out.
You have to have
an inner strength
to do that.
We discovered Jim
just like the world did.
He was truly
a man for others.
Nicole:
Witnessing Jim's murder
this publicly.
it sends a message
to all of us.
And my. I guess.
response to that
is having lost
so many friends
and knowing that people
are purposely out
for journalists now.
I mean.
we have to fight back
with our pictures
and our words.
I don't want to
let them win.
Clare:
The extent to which the media
coverage took off.
it was just staggering.
It was absolutely
staggering.
Something like
94% of Americans
were aware of Jim's death
and how he died.
It's the event with
the second most recognition
in recent American history
after 9/11.
He would have been
horrified by that.
I mean. he was there to talk
about the Syrian people
and this is the takeaway.
Brian:
What is your response
to people
who would say he shouldn't
have been in there?
Clare:
My response is do you
read the newspaper?
Do you watch TV?
You're depending on someone
to bring you
that information.
If you care about
what's going on in Syria.
you don't have
the right to be like.
"Oh. why's he there?"
How do you even
know what there is?
Because he told you.
Pierre:
I remember the video.
and there was a desert.
And in the background
you could see that
the desert stopped.
and there was all
the Valley of Euphrates.
So. according to what
I know from James.
I'm. like. 100% sure
that even though
he was convinced he would
be killed.
he enjoyed the view.
Nicolas:
He died as a free man.
This is not the death
of a hostage.
And this is the difference.
eventually.
between Jim and myself.
I ended up being released.
but he ended up free.
Daniel:
And when we came
to James' funeral.
everything started to become
real again in a way.
The fact that I managed
to say good-bye
to James together
with all his loved ones
was really powerful.
It reminded me
how important it was that--
that. James. he gave
that letter to me.
Michael:
"Dear family and friends.
I remember going to
the mall with Dad.
a very long
bike ride with Mom.
I remember so many
great family times
that take me away
from this prison.
Dreams of family
and friends take me away
and happiness
fills my heart.
I know you're thinking
of me and praying for me.
and I am so thankful.
I feel you all.
especially when I pray.
I pray for you
to stay strong
and to believe.
I really feel
I can touch you.
even in this darkness.
when I pray.
I think a lot about
my brothers and sister.
I remember playing werewolf
in the dark with Michael
and so many other
adventures.
I think of chasing
Matty and T. around
the kitchen counter.
It makes me happy
to think of them.
If there is any money
left in my bank account.
I want it to go
to Michael and Matthew.
I am so proud of you.
Michael.
and thankful to you
for happy childhood memories
and to you and Kristie
for happy adult ones.
And. Big John.
how I enjoyed visiting you
and Cress in Germany.
Thank you
for welcoming me.
I think a lot about RoRo
and try to imagine
what Jack is like.
I hope he has RoRo's
personality.
Priest:
So. Mark and Kasey.
what name have you
given your son?
James Michael Foley.
Michael:
And. Mark. so proud
of you. too. bro.
I think of you
on the West Coast
and hope you're doing some
snowboarding and camping.
I especially remember us
going to the comedy club
in Boston together
and our big hug after.
The special moments
keep me hopeful.
Katie. so very
proud of you.
You are the strongest
and best of us all.
I think of you
working so hard
helping people
as a nurse.
I pray I can come
to your wedding.
Now I'm sounding
like Grammy.
Grammy. please
take your medicine.
Take walks
and keep dancing.
I plan to take you out to
Margaritas when I get home.
Stay strong. because I am
going to need your help
to reclaim my life.
Jim."
♪ If I should
close my eyes ♪
♪ That my soul can see ♪
♪ There's a place
at the table ♪
♪ That you save for me ♪
♪ So many thousand miles ♪
♪ Over land and sea ♪
♪ I hope true. dear ♪
♪ That you hear my prayer ♪
♪ And somehow I'll be there ♪
♪ There's but
a concrete floor ♪
♪ Where my head will lay ♪
♪ And though the walls
of this prison ♪
♪ Are as cold as clay ♪
♪ But there's a shaft
of light ♪
♪ Where I count my days ♪
♪ So don't despair ♪
♪ Of the empty chair ♪
♪ And somehow
I'll be there ♪
♪ Some days I'm strong ♪
♪ Some days I'm weak ♪
♪ On days when I'm broken.
I can barely speak ♪
♪ But that place in my head ♪
♪ Where my thoughts
still roam ♪
♪ Somehow I've come home ♪
♪ And when the winter comes ♪
♪ And the trees lie bare ♪
♪ And you just stare
out the window ♪
♪ In the darkness there ♪
♪ Well. I was always late ♪
♪ For every meal
you'll swear ♪
♪ But keep my place ♪
♪ On the empty chair ♪
♪ And somehow I'll be there ♪
♪ And somehow I'll be there. ♪
( music playing )
Do you want subtitles for any video?
-=[ ai.OpenSubtitles.com ]=-